Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - Tucker, Adeline, 2004 November 19; computer file (WAV)
    Adeline Tucker was born and raised in the Dixwell neighborhood of New Haven then married and raised children in the city during the 1960s and 1970s. She discusses her memories of that period. An African American woman, Tucker took an interest in civil rights issues as a teenager. Her older brother was chair of the local branch of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and she became a member. Her brother forbade her to travel to the South with him to protest, but she participated in sit-ins in New Haven. As an adult, she became a member of First and Summerfield Church because she appreciated its social activism, its interracial congregation, and the political engagement of its pastor, Jim Davis. Tucker discusses the convergence of the Civil Rights movement with the anti-Vietnam demonstrations. Tucker was active in civil rights work. While she opposed the war, she felt that many antiwar demonstrators did not support soldiers and thus did not demonstrate against it. She discusses her impressions of the Black Panthers, whom she considered too militant. She remembers the May Day demonstrations in 1970 but did not take part because she stayed at home with her young children. She also comments favorably on Yale President Kingman Brewster and the student activists of the 1960s and 1970s.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Twyman, Charles, 2004 March 26; computer file (WAV)
    Charles Twyman, born in New Haven, discusses the ethnic enclaves in his neighborhood in the early 1920s, consisting of German- and Irish-Americans and, to a lesser extent, African-Americans. He shares anecdotes about his childhood friends and neighbors. Twyman details his experiences as a soldier in the Army during World War II. He describes the effects of segregationist military policies on his interactions with his white peers and their effects on the perception of unity, purpose, and patriotism among his black peers. Recalling the phrase, "We don't take colored," he details the irony of encountering exemplary black soldiers, including the 10th Cavalry (the "Buffalo Soldiers"), who, because of their race, were largley relegated to service positions. He describes adjusting to civilian life after the army. He used the GI Bill of Rights to go to New Haven State Teacher's College, now Southern Connecticut University, taught at an integrated elementary school, and later got involved in local politics. He shares stories about his experiential teaching methods, including class visits to the courthouse and hospital. He recalls his confrontations with the racist attitudes and actions of some of his students. He talks about the permeability of segregation in all aspects of life, including local businesses and other public areas. He discusses his role as the Chairman of the Dixwell Community Council amidst Mayor Lee's urban renewal policies, describing his efforts to address the negative reactions of displaced residents including Black Coalition members.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Twyman, Charles, 2004 October 13; computer file (WAV)
    Length (min): 80, 20
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Tyler, Cheever, 2006 March 15; computer file (WAV)
    Cheever Tyler, who grew up in California, moved to New Haven in 1964 to practice law. Beforehand, he attended Yale University, Michigan Law School, and served in the Navy. He describes what drew him to law, mentioning its political and policy foundations and its community interactions. He discusses his decision to move to New Haven after clerking at a New York law firm, preferring New Haven's urban resources, small-town familiarity, artistic venues, and community service networks. He reflects upon his thirty-year career at New Haven corporate law firm Wiggin & Dana, which he describes as creating "a real sense of community." He compares the practices and traits of small/rural and big/urban law firms, discussing differences in popular cases, working environments, and community interactions. He shares anecdotes illustrating the professional and personal qualities of several of his most successful peers, including John Barnett, Dick Bell, Dick Bowerman, Bill Cavanaugh, and the late Newt Schenck. He provides other examples of lawyers in different settings and career junctures who devotedl time to community service. He also discusses the growing difficulty of offering pro bono services amidst inflation and rising professional costs. Tyler discusses his interpretation of the varying aspects of volunteerism in the legal practice and the professional and ethical responsibilities of lawyers. He talks fondly about the collegiality among lawyers within and among firms and the role of lawyers as participants in the larger community.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Vargas, Moses, 2007 February 17; computer file (WAV)
    Moses Vargas, born in Michoacan, a Mexican state, has lived in East Haven since 1986, before which he lived in New York City and North Branford. A cook and Mexican restaurant owner, Vargas describes several of his signature ingredients, recipes, and cooking methods inspired by his mother and grandmother. He reflects upon his happiness with his job, including the regular customers, the safe neighborhood, and the opportunity to improve his cooking skills by participating in competitions. He recalls that his interest in cooking came not from any formal training but after his brother helped him get a job as a dishwasher in a New York country club. He also describes his business' challenges, including the difficulty of financially managing during the winter, when many of his Mexican customers return to Mexico for the warm weather. He talks about the difficulty of not being able to open restaurants in surrounding cities because of permit complications. Still, he describes cooking as both a passion and a responsibility, giving him a sense of self and allowing him to support his wife and two children. He struggles with whether he considers Mexico or the United States his real "home," and what that means. But he maintains that while living in Mexico among extended family members gives his family sentimental and cultural value, living in the United States provides his family with political liberties, economic stability, and educational opportunities. He describes the economic, political, and cultural differences between his neighborhood in Michoacan and that in East Haven and the changes he's noticed in both over the years.
    Interviewer: Cohen, Rachel
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Vitelli, Eugene, 2004 October 24; computer file (WAV)
    Eugene Vitelli, born and raised in New Haven, describes his forty-year career as a teacher and administrator in several New Haven high schools: Hillhouse High School, Fair Haven, and Wilbur Cross. He describes the 1967 and 1970 black student-led, Black-Panther influenced race riots at Hillhouse, and explains what he thinks led to the riots. He mentions that some black students felt that Hillhouse staff favored and spent more time with white students, using more resources to help them prepare for college students than those on black students. He also mentions that some black students believed that the mainly white teachers overlooked and omitted black literature in the English and history curriculum, overlooking minority, and especially black, experiences and viewpoints. He adds that he believes that part of the staff's greater emphasis on white students and Anglo-American curricula stemmed from their unfamiliarity and discomfort in interacting with minority students. In discussing the varied reactions to the riots, Vitelli recalls his own efforts to address student complaints and restore school order. These efforts, he concedes, were unconvincing to the many white students who chose to transfer from Hillhouse to other high schools, such as Richard C. Lee High school, Notre Dame High School, and Ezra Academy, which soon became overwhelmingly white. He reflects that the black majority student body at Hillhouse is still apparent today. Vitelli recalls the difficulty of negotiating with white and black students, teachers, administrators, police, and parents, each of whom had different opinions of the cause of the riots and different visions for its settlement.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Vitelli, Gene, 2003 July 14; computer file (WAV)
  - Voigt, Susan, 2007 May 2; computer file (WAV)
    Susan Voigt was the child of Jewish immigrant parents, born three years after the family's arrival in the United States. After graduating from college, she opened a restaurant on Grand Avenue in Fair Haven with her older brother, who had previous experience in the nightclub business. At the time of the interview, Voigt's restaurant had been in operation for 27 years, surviving a number of economic downturns and the changing demographics of Fair Haven. She describes a failed 1990s attempt to gentrify Fair Haven, suggesting that such good natured designs might be effective in theory, but stumbled in practice. Even so, Voigt describes a remarkable resurgence in Fair Haven over the last eight or so years. This improvement was not necessarily government led, but resulted from Fair Haven residents taking responsibility for cleaning up their own communities. Voigt talks about the importance of home ownership to community morale. She describes her family's immigration experience, and suggests the importance of immigration to the culture of Fair Haven over the years.
    Length (min): 45
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Walker, Paula, 2007 April 12; computer file (WAV)
    Paula Walker moved from New York to New Haven in the late 1990s, and now lives with her family in the Chatham Square neighborhood in Fair Haven. Walker describes a divide in her neighborhood between residents who own their own homes, and those who rent homes from absentee landlords. The latter class, Walker suggests, tends to be less invested in the upkeep of their residences, and less engaged with the health of the community. Walker organizes weekly events for children in a Fair Haven park in order to encourage community. Walker is also active in the Community Foundation, a grassroots community organization dedicated to Fair Haven. Walker mentions that the New Haven Police Department tends to ignore Fair Haven, suggesting that "unless you're selling drugs or getting shot the cops usually don't respond very fast to most things here." In general, Walker is proud of her neighborhood and pleased to live with there. With a little more pride and respect on the part of certain residents, she suggests, Chatham Square could be made even better.
    Length (min): 103
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Wasserman, Elga, 2004 November 24; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Haves, Arielle
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Webber, Malcom, 2007 February 6; computer file (WAV)
    After serving in Europe in World War II, Malcolm Webber moved to New Haven in 1968 to work for the Anti-Defamation League, which he describes as the "community relations agency" for the Jewish community of Connecticut. When the movement to erect a Holocaust memorial in New Haven got underway, Webber and his wife involved themselves immediately. On a trip to Europe, Webber visited Auschwitz. He collected some dirt which, he says, contained the ashes of Holocaust victims. Webber brought the ashes back to New Haven, where they were interred below the memorial. In addition, Webber discusses his efforts to write a Holocaust unit for use in Connecticut schools, which, up to that point, had failed to provide sufficient coverage. He describes the birth of the Yale Holocaust survivors video collection, which provided an opportunity for local survivors to share their testimony, and a means to ensure that these stories were not lost to history. Webber and his wife, who is present for most of the interview, compare their impressions of the Holocaust to other genocides in the world today.
    Interviewer: Ruben-Cadrain, Leah
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Wessel, Paul, 2007 March 29; computer file (WAV)
    Paul Wessel talks about empowering and organizing communities and small business owners in and near New Haven. He discusses his experiences developing, organizing, and improving merchant organizations. He mentions the Livable City Initiative, an anti-blight urban housing program, and GAVA, the Grand Avenue Village Association, an organization of local merchants along Grand Avenue. He talks about common platform issues in both organizations, such as health care and health insurance, municipal planning and economic development, immigrant involvement and representation, city-hired instead of locally hired employees, and negotiation among contesting visions of progress and fairness. He details his leadership roles in GAVA and its past and current aims, strengths, and weaknesses. He discusses its collaborations with other labor initiatives, such as SAMA, the Spanish American Merchant Association. He talks about interacting socially and politically with business owners and aldermen to continue the economic development of New Haven and Fair Haven communities.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Whitlock, Manson, 2004 February 4; computer file (WAV)
    From the 1950s through the early 2000s, Manson Witlock operated a typewriter repair shop on Broadway Street and later York Street. He discusses his life as a small business owner in New Haven and the changes that he has seen living in the area for over seventy years. Whitlock's father owned a turkey farm in Bethany and his family also owned bookstores in Bethany. Whitlock begins by talking about the 1950s and the election of Mayor Richard C. Lee, one of his classmates at Hillhouse High School. Whitlock talks a bit about Lee's urban renewal projects but says that he did not feel that affected by him. However, he admits missing the shopping in department stores that were demolished as part of the redevelopment work. He cites Yale's decision to become co-educational as a major turning point in the downtown and campus environment. His interview touches on the race riots and the tensions of the 1960s and 1970s, but Whitlock maintains that he tried to simply ignore the turmoil as much as he could. He remained busy until the 1980s, when computers began to replace typewriters. Rent spikes in the 1990s also affected his business. But at the time of the interview in 2004 he continued to service typewriters.
    Interviewer: Toomajian, Martin
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Winnick, Ed, 2006 April 12; computer file (WAV)
    Ed Winnick grew up in Woodbridge and New Haven. He attended Dartmouth College, served as an officer in the U.S. Navy, and went to Yale Law School. He talks about what drew him to law school, identifying his law-practicing family members as influences. He discusses working for his first law firm, Winnick & Winnick, and focusing on negligence practice. He mentions several specific cases undertaken by his firm over the years. He talks about the congeniality he's encountered between lawyers within and among firms, listing peers he described as successful lawyers, such as Morris Tyler. He describes the historic ethnic and religious exclusivity of lawyer-populated country clubs. Ironically, it is this exclusivity that was a product of the congeniality that created and enhanced legal relationships. He talks about representing small Jewish businesses and the extent that legal decisions may affect personal relationships, and vice versa.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Wolff, Karen, 2005 February 28; computer file (WAV)
    Karen Wolffe, who came to New Haven in 1969, helped found High School in the Community. HSC focused on teaching by experience instead of memorization. She recalls how her experiences as a civil rights worker in SNCC influenced her vision of schools and teachers exposing young people to tolerance. She talks about the reaction of outside school officials to HSC's no-textbook curriculum, open-ended teaching methods and philosophy, and its lack of administrators. She describes the challenges and rewards of founding a school and academically and personally interacting with unmotivated students. She talks about the classroom as a community in which students learn about and from each other. She shares anecdotes describing her efforts to make her curriculum applicable to her students' daily lives. She discusses the cultural implications of standardized testing, particularly the SAT, saying that they either test or affirm upper middle class abilities.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Zakur, David, 2007 February 9; computer file (WAV)
    David Zakur, born in Boston, grew up in Branford. He recalls visiting New Haven often for recreation with his mother, describing the local New Haven businesses popular during his youth. He talks about his frequent moves around the New Haven area and the country, settling in Fair Haven since 1993. He describes his current Fair Haven neighborhood, specifically the community's efforts to make it safer, more functional, and more aesthetic. He discusses the personal connections among neighbors that unite the community to address issues of home improvement and neighborhood security. He talks about collaborating with other community organizations in and outside the Fair Haven area and the development of solidarity and familiarity among neighbors. He discusses recent projects to make the neighborhood safe through street, home, and traffic renovations. He talks about challenges still facing the community, including drug use and prostitution, but, in such cases, reflects upon the effectiveness of communication over confrontation.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Zamkov, Shifre, 2005 November 22; computer file (WAV)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Zelinsky, Doris, 2005 October 28; computer file (WAV)
    Doris Zelinsky, the daughter of Polish Holocaust survivors, was a member of the first class of women admitted to Yale College. After graduating, Zelinsky remained in New Haven to work for the Office of Policy Analysis under Mayor Frank Logue and became involved with the erection of a memorial to Holocaust survivors in the city. Zelinsky tells the story of a day in late 1976 when a group of survivors and members of the New Haven Jewish Federation came to the Mayor's office to ask for a parcel of city land on which to build the memorial. Zelinsky explains that this was an unusual request because the monument was not for people from New Haven and because there were few similar memorials in the United States at the time. She remembers that the proposal confused some people, such as Logue's assistant Rosa DeLauro. But, she recounts, Mayor Logue took great interest in the proposal and helped see it through to its inauguration the following year. She discusses her experiences as the commemoration ceremony and its rededication ceremony in 1981. Zelinsky further recounts Logue's commitment to the proposal and the culture of monument building in the United States at the time. She also talks about her parents' experiences as survivors and the stories that she heard from other survivors growing up. Finally, she discusses her involvement in the creation of a video documentary to capture the oral histories of survivors. Ed Zelinsky, her husband and an Alderman, helped with this project.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Zelinsky, Ed, 2006 November 15; computer file (WAV)
    Ed Zelinsky left Omaha to attend Yale College in 1968, then graduated from Yale Law School and remained in New Haven as an attorney and a member of the Board of Alderman. He discusses his childhood and adult involvement in Jewish affairs, his entry into city politics in the 1970s and his involvement in the construction of the Holocaust Memorial at Edgewood Park. Zelinsky discusses the political climate of the 1970s. Running as a reform Democrat, he became the first Yale student elected to the Board of Alderman. He shared this political affiliation with friend Frank Logue, who beat incumbent Bart Guida in the 1975 mayoral race. Zelinsky then discusses his role in appealing for the Holocaust Memorial. The New Haven Jewish Federation brought the proposal for the memorial to Mayor Logue in 1976. Although they proposed the New Haven Green for the site initially, the city ultimately decided to construct it in Edgewood Park. This was part of Zelinksy's Aldermanic ward so he represented his constituency in favoring the project. He recounts Frank Logue's support for the project, his memories o the 1977 dedication ceremony, and his views on the 1981 expansion of the memorial.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)